# **Curriculum Vitae**

#### **PROFILE**

Health economics PhD student with knowledge in health economic evaluation, health care management and health economics based on courses offered at university and 5-year research experience; trained in econometrics; health economic modelling; discrete choice experiments; and data visualization; knowledge of and interest in well-being research, evaluation of health care programs and products, estimating the monetary value of health, and health state valuation.

#### **EDUCATION**

09/2017-present

#### PhD Candidate, Erasmus University Rotterdam

Erasmus School of Health Policy & Management, Health Economics Section PhD thesis scheduled to be submitted in March 2022

#### Thesis topic:

"Valuing health & well-being - Extending the scope and empirical basis of health economic evaluations."

In my doctorate, I am applying economic and statistical tools, including applied econometrics, health economic modelling, and discrete choice experiments, to conduct research on topics surrounding tools to inform the efficient allocation of health care resources. This especially includes eliciting preferences on the importance of different (health-related) quality of life dimensions and obtaining societal monetary valuations of health and well-being gains.

#### 09/2017-12/2020 Marie Curie Fellow

European Training Network - Improving Quality of Care in Europe "IQCE" (https://www.iqce.eu/). Funded by the European Union's Horizon 2020 research and innovation programme under the Marie Sklodowska-Curie grant agreement No 721402.

#### 04/2013-05/2016 M.Sc. Health Economics, University of Bayreuth, Germany

Overall GPA: 1.4 (First Class)

Thesis: "Does the introduction of a prospective payment system influence the length of stay in hospitals? A quantitative analysis using aggregated data from Germany" (Supervisor: Andreas Schmid; grade: 1.0)

#### 08/2014-05/2015 Visiting Scholar, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

Gillings School of Global Public Health, Department of Health Policy and Management

## 10/2009-04/2013 B.Sc. Health Economics, University of Bayreuth, Germany

Overall GPA: 2.4 (Second class – upper division)

#### Peer-Reviewed Journal Articles

- **Himmler, S.**, Jonker, M., van Krugten, F., et al. Estimating an anchored utility tariff for the well-being of older people measure (WOOP) for the Netherlands. *Soc Sci Med*, 301:114901 (2022). https://doi.org/10.1016/j.socscimed.2022.114901
- Phillips, E.A., **Himmler, S.**, Schreyögg, J.: Preferences of psychotherapists for blended care in Germany: a discrete choice experiment. BMC Psychiatry. 22, 1–12 (2022). https://doi.org/10.1186/s12888-022-03765-x
- **Himmler, S.,** van Exel, J., Brouwer, W.: Did the COVID-19 pandemic change the willingness to pay for an early warning system for infectious diseases in Europe? *Eur. J. Heal. Econ.* (2021). https://doi.org/10.1007/s10198-021-01353-6
- Enzing, J.J., **Himmler, S.,** Knies, S., Brouwer, W.B.F.: Do Profit Margins of Pharmaceuticals Influence Reimbursement Decisions? A Discrete Choice Experiment Among Dutch Healthcare Decision Makers. *Value Heal.* (2021). https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jval.2021.08.007
- **Himmler, S.**, Stöckel, J., van Exel, J., Brouwer, W. The value of health—Empirical issues when estimating the monetary value of a quality-adjusted life year based on well-being data. *Health Economics* (2021). https://doi.org/10.1002/hec.4279
- Phillips, E., **Himmler, S.,** Schreyögg, J. Preferences for e-Mental Health Interventions in Germany: A Discrete Choice Experiment. *Value in Health* 24(3), 421-430 (2021). https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jval.2020.09.018
- **Himmler, S.**, Soekhai, V., van Exel, J., Brouwer, W.: What works better for preference elicitation among older people? Cognitive burden of discrete choice experiment and case 2 best-worst scaling in an online setting. *J. Choice Model.* 38, 100265 (2021). https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jocm.2020.100265
- **Himmler, S.**, Branner, J.C., Ostwald, D.A.: The societal impact of a biologic treatment of ankylosing spondylitis: a case study based on secukinumab. *J. Comp. Eff. Res.* (2020). https://doi.org/10.2217/cer-2020-0077
- **Himmler, S.**, Mueller, M., Sherif, B., Ostwald, D.: A case study applying a novel approach to estimate the social impact of a medical innovation the use of secukinumab for psoriatic arthritis in Germany. *Expert Rev. Pharmacoeconomics Outcomes Res.* 20, 369–378 (2020). https://doi.org/10.1080/14737167.2019.1644169
- Hofmann, S., **Himmler, S.**, Ostwald, D., Dünzinger, U., Launonen, A., Thuresson, P.-O.: The societal impact of obinutuzumab in the first-line treatment of patients with follicular lymphoma in Germany. *J. Comp. Eff. Res.* 9, (2020). https://doi.org/10.2217/cer-2020-0131
- **Himmler, S.**, van Exel, J., Brouwer, W.: Estimating the monetary value of health and capability well-being applying the well-being valuation approach. *Eur. J. Heal. Econ.* (2020). https://doi.org/10.1007/s10198-020-01231-7
- **Himmler, S.**, Exel, J. Van, Brouwer, W.: Happy with Your Capabilities? Valuing ICECAP-O and ICECAP-A States Based on Experienced Utility Using Subjective Well-Being Data. *Med. Decis. Mak.* 1–13 (2020). https://doi.org/10.1177/0272989X20923015
- Himmler, S., van Exel, J., Perry-Duxbury, M., Brouwer, W.: Willingness to pay for an early warning system for infectious diseases. *Eur. J. Heal. Econ.* (2020). https://doi.org/10.1007/s10198-020-01171-2
- **Himmler, S.**, Müller, M., Ostwald, D., Seddik, A., Basic, E., Hradetzky, E.: Long-term health benefits of stroke prevention with apixaban versus vitamin K antagonist warfarin in patients with non-valvular atrial fibrillation in Germany: a population-based modelling study. *Expert Rev. Pharmacoeconomics Outcomes Res.* 19, (2019). https://doi.org/10.1080/14737167.2019.1522501

- Reichert, A., Fröhlich, J., **Himmler, S.**, Krauth, C., Amelung, V.E.: Health economic potentials of an integrated poststroke care management approach | Gesundheitsökonomische Potenziale einer ganzheitlichen Nachsorge von Schlaganfallpatienten. *Gesundheitsokonomie und Qual.* 22, 297–305 (2017).
- Davis, S.A., **Himmler, S.**, Feldman, S.R.: Cost-effectiveness analysis of using dermatologists versus pediatricians to treat mild to moderate acne. *Dermatol. Online J.* 23, 0–11 (2017)

#### Book chapters and reports

- **Himmler S.**: Estimating the monetary value of health: why and how. In: Schildmann J., Buch C., Zerth J. (Ed.): Defining the Value of Medical Interventions Normative and Empirical Challenges. Kohlhammer Verlag (2021).
- Amelung V., **Himmler S.**, Stein V.: Strategic Management and Integrated Care in a Competitive Environment. In: Amelung V. (Ed.): Handbook Integrated Care. Springer Verlag (2017).
- Neumann K., Stibbe H., Ostwald D., **Himmler S.**, Müller M., Damm O., Scholz S., Greiner W: Entwicklung des Gesundheitsnutzens Veränderung der Krankheitslast von 1993 bis 2013 für ausgewählte Krankheitsbilder. Study report for the Bundesverbandes der deutschen Industrie e.V. (BDI) (2017).
- Schmid A., **Himmler S.**: Netzwerkmedizin Impulse für Deutschland aus den USA. Project report for the Münch Foundation (Stiftung Münch) (2015). Available at: http://www.stiftung-muench.org/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/StudieUSA.pdf.
- **Himmler S.**, Jugl M.: Hospital Costs in the USA and Germany. In: Schmid A. and Fried B. (Ed.): Crossing Borders Health Reform in the U.S. Schriften zur Gesundheitsökonomie, vol. 82, pp. 41-56 (2015).

#### **REVIEWING ACTIVITIES**

Economics & Human Biology (1)

European Journal of Health Economics (2)

Value in Health (2)

Health Economics (1)

Population Health Metrics (1)

#### **FURTHER RESEARCH EXPERIENCE**

### 07/2016-12/2018 Research Associate, WifOR GmbH, Darmstadt, Germany

Health Economic research

- Working in and leading of research projects measuring the societal impact of different innovations on productivity by adopting and developing health economic models, creating population models and establishing a link between clinical outcomes and productivity
- Performing societal benefit-cost analysis and accounting for uncertainty through probabilistic sensitivity analysis
- Assisting in developing a burden of disease analysis for type 2 diabetes in Germany

# 12/2015-05/2016 Student Assistant, Hannover Medical School (MHH), Hannover, Germany Institute of Epidemiology and Health Systems Research

- Writing of research proposals for the German Innovation Fund

- Drafting publications and preparing presentations for international conferences

06-10/2015 Internship, inav-GmbH (Institut für angewandte Versorgungsforschung), Berlin, Germany

Research Assistant for health economic modeling and evaluation

- Conducting literature reviews using PubMed for two indications to gather input parameters for health economic models

- Developing an economic model for the post-acute care of stroke in Germany and adopting a costeffectiveness model from the British to the German context

#### **TEACHING EXPERIENCE**

2021	Tutor, Erasmus School of Health Policy & Management Advanced research methods
2020; 2022	Tutor, Erasmus School of Health Policy & Management Measuring patient preferences using Discrete Choice Experiments
2019-2021	Tutor, Erasmus School of Health Policy & Management Global Health Economics
2019-2022	Supervisor, Erasmus School of Health Policy & Management Master thesis supervision (9)
2019	Tutor, Erasmus School of Health Policy & Management Quantitative Research Methods
05-08/2015	Student Assistant, University of Bayreuth, Bayreuth, Germany STATA instructor for Empirical Health Economics

#### **SKILLS**

Methodology: Discrete choice experiments, Statistical modelling using Markov chains and decision trees, survey design,

linear and non-linear regression analysis, panel data analysis, theory of economics of health and health care

Software: STATA, R, Ngene (DCE design software), Lighthouse Sawtooth (Survey software)

Languages: German (mother tongue), English (business fluent), French (beginner), Dutch (beginner)

#### PROFESSIONAL AND ASSOCIATION MEMBERSHIPS

Working group of health economics and management (AKGM e.V., Bayreuth)

German Society for Health Economics (DGGÖ)

Open Science Community Rotterdam (OSCR)

Erasmus Choice Modelling Center (ECMC)